Preliminary Inventory of the B. E. (B. Edwin) Hutchinson Papers 1914-1961
Hoover Institution Archives
B. E. (B. Edwin) Hutchinson papers
1914-1961
97027
Hutchinson, B. E. (B. Edwin), 1888-1961
40 manuscript boxes (16.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, financial records, and printed matter, relating to industrial and labor policy in the United States, the promotion of free enterprise and conservative thought, and activities of the Chrysler Corporation, the Foundation for Economic Education, and the National Council of Churches.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1997.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
American business executive; vice president, Chrysler Corporation, 1925-1955; chairman of the board, Foundation for Economic Education; vice president, National Council of Churches.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, financial records, and printed matter, relating to industrial and labor policy in the United States, the promotion of free enterprise and conservative thought, and activities of the Chrysler Corporation, the Foundation for Economic Education, and the National Council of Churches.
Access Points
Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Industries--United States.; Labor policy--United States.; Conservatism.; Laissez-faire.; United States--Religion.; United States--Economic conditions.; United States--Politics and government.; Chrysler Corporation.; Foundation for Economic Education, inc.; National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America.
Container List
- General Correspondence, March - June 1956, arranged alphabetically, Economic Club of Detroit to J. Howard Pew (the Bishop Emerich European Trip Fund). (Box 1)
- General Correspondence, March - June 1956, J. Howard Pew to Mrs. Mark J. Woodhull. Separate folders of correspondence with the American Enterprise Association, the Parishfield Conference, the Spiritual Mobilization (Los Angeles), the Tax Foundation, and St. Paul's Cathedral (Detroit) Endowment Fund. (Box 2)
- General private correspondence, 1950-1955. Significant correspondents include Sen. Robert A. Taft, Sen. Stuart Symington, and noted conservative Russell Kirk. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and reports, 1959; Extensive files on the Tax Foundation and St. Paul's Cathedral (Detroit), including recordings of telephone conversations; daily appointment book, 1954. (Box 4)
- General correspondence, 1959. Large files on the Foundation for Economic Education. Box includes Hutchinson's lecture of 13 December 1932, "The Automobile's Challenge to America's Transportation Policy" at the Princeton University School of Engineering, 13 December 1932 and "Some Observations on Troublesome Questions," an address to the Michigan Commercial Secretaries Association on 29 April 1952 at the Hotel Statler, Washington, D.C. (Box 5)
- Personal correspondence, 1953, much of it related to Hutchinson's illness and hospitalization for ulcers. Includes about six conservative tracts and speeches, including a September 1944 speech by George Romney (Automobile Council for War Production) regarding postwar reconversion. Includes a small book by Theodore Iserman and Leo Wolman, Industrial Peace and the Wagner Act, How the Act Works and What to Do About It (1947). This is one of over one hundred anti-labor union tracts and books which are found in this collection. (Box 6)
- Conservative tracts or lectures (see separate listing) (Box 7)
- Conservative tracts or lectures (see separate listing) (Box 8)
- Conservative tracts or lectures (see separate listing) (Box 9)
- Conservative tracts or lectures (see separate listing) (Box 10)
- Personal and organizational correspondence, 1958. (Box 11)
- Personal and organizational correspondence, 1953, including correspondence with the Rev. Richard S. M. Emrich, Episcopal Bishop of Michigan. Separate files for the Foundation For Economic Education for 1955, 1956, and 1958. Hutchinson served as a trustee for this conservative economic "think tank" with its headquarters in Irvington-on-Hudson, New York. (Box 12)
- General Correspondence, 1951, but primarily 1958. The materials from 1951 all relate to the Foundation For Economic Education and include the Foundation's history, budgets, etc. (Box 13)
- Foundation For Economic Education materials for 1948-1953, including reports from annual meetings, lists of donors, and financial information. (Box 14)
- Foundation For Economic Education materials, June 1946 through 1949, including correspondence and various publications. (Box 15)
- Daily appointment books, 1957, 1958, 1960. Correspondence, 1957, relating to the MIT Corporation (Hutchinson was one of 61 active members), the Foundation For Economic Education, and other miscellaneous correspondence. (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous personal and political correspondence, 1957, including correspondence with Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. Detailed listing of Hutchinson's Christmas gifts (cash) and various contributions, 1955-1957. (Box 17)
- Foundation For Economic Education files, 1953, 1954 [includes budgets, meetings of the Board of Directors, etc.]; St Paul's Cathedral, Detroit, for 1957; charitable contributions, 1957; miscellaneous correspondence, 1961. (Box 18)
- Contributions for 1961; spreadsheet of Hutchinson's charitable contributions, 1944-1961; correspondence for 1959-1961 (mainly 1961) arranged in folders alphabetically (A to S); Economic Club of Detroit materials (Hutchinson was a director); St. Paul's Cathedral, Detroit, including financial reports for 1960, 1961; and "Rotating Vestry Matter" (at St. Paul's), 1957-1959 (Hutchinson was a member of the Cathedral Vestry). (Box 19)
- Correspondence for 1961, alphabetically in folders T - W; correspondence, in folders (Bishop Emrich - MIT); and large folder on the Foundation For Economic Education, including lists of donors for 1959-1961. (Box 20)
- Miscellaneous correspondence. 1956, 1957, including numerous letters to various Protestant churches regarding evangelical Christianity; loose correspondence for 1957, Diocese of Michigan to Frances, James; materials relating the to Spiritual Mobilization; and miscellaneous political tracts. (Box 21)
- National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A., 1956-1957. Hutchinson resigned as a vice president on 20 September 1957 because of the lack of lay involvement in the NCC. (Box 22)
- National Council of Churches materials, including financial reports for 1955-1957. Much discussion of the NCC taking a political position on state "right to work" laws. (Box 23)
- National Council of Churches materials, 1952-1954; Hutchinson's obituary; Hutchinson speeches: "Building Solidly For Permanent Prosperity," Association of National Advertisers, Detroit, Michigan, 27 April 1937; "The Automobile's Challenge to America's Transportation Policy,"; and "Christianity, Democracy, and Capitalism Are the Foundation Upon Which the Hope of Human Progress Rests," at the Chrysler Institute of Engineering, 22 June 1944; Richard S. Emrich, Bishop of Michigan, "Sermon Preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Paul at the Burial Office for B.E. Hutchinson, September 30, 1961." (Box 24)
- Hutchinson Speeches, March 1943 - October 1952 (see separate listing) (Box 25)
- Hutchinson Speeches, February 1937 - April 1953 (see separate listing) (Box 26)
- Hutchinson Speeches, August 1943 - October 1952 (see separate listing) (Box 27)
- General Correspondence, 1959-1961, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, M to Z, for 1960. (Box 28)
- General Correspondence for 1960, American Enterprise Institute to Murray, including extensive files for the Foundation For Economic Education. The beginning of documents related to the Chrysler Corporation, including letters from 30 March 1923 on. Folder of correspondence with K.T. Keller covers March 1941 through February 1954 and includes an audio recording of a phone conversation between Hutchinson and K.T. Keller, 26 July 1950, 3:00 PM., (31 letters) (Box 29)
- Hutchinson's appointment calendars, 1952-1956, 1958-1960; correspondence with Louis H.T. Dehmlow, 1959-1960 (ca.); Hutchinson's Christmas letters, December 1960 (ca. 175 in all); and miscellaneous conservative tracts (see separate listing)., 50 letters (Box 30)
- Maxwell Motor Company Annual Reports for Year Ending 31 July 1914 though 31 July 1918; Maxwell Motor Corporation, Consolidated Balance Sheets, 31 December 1921 through 31 December 1924; Chrysler Corporation Consolidated Balance Sheets, 31 December 1925 through 31 December 1927; Chrysler Corporation Annual Reports, Year Ended 31 December 1928 through Year Ended 31 December 1950; and "Printed Speeches, Material About Chrysler Corporation and Automobile Industry Suitable for Mail" (see separate listing). (Box 31)
- Chrysler Corporation Annual Reports for Year Ended 31 December 1951 though 31 December 1953; Financial Statement (quarterly) for 1951, 1952, and 1953; and various Chrysler Corporation printed materials (see separate listing). (Box 32)
- Maxwell Motor Company Annual Report for Year Ended 31 July 1918; Chrysler Corporation, Consolidated Balance Sheets, 1925-1927; Annual Reports, 1928-1950; Financial Quarterly Reports, 1949, 1950; Folder, "Notices to Employees," includes notices regarding stock, savings, and investment plans (1 July 1929), Employee Representation in the Plants of Chrysler Motors (October 1929), and bonus pay announcements, March 1934; Chrysler Corporation Certificate of Incorporation (6 June 1925) and Amendments (23 December 1925 - 25 April 1949); Chrysler Corporation By-Laws, adopted 6 June 1925, with twelve amendments through 24 September 1953; and Dodge Brothers, Inc., Indenture, 15 April 1925. (Box 33)
- Printed conservative tracts (see separate listing). (Box 34)
- Printed materials authored by Chrysler officials and others (see separate listing). (Box 35)
- Printed conservative tracts (see separate listing). (Box 36)
- Printed conservative tracts (see separate listing). (Box 37)
- General Correspondence, arranged alphabetically, Albany, NY Congress to St. Pauls' Cathedral, 1955. Includes extensive correspondence with the American Enterprise Association (Hutchinson was a trustee); Automotive Safety Foundation; Campaign For the 48 States (states' rights); Economic Club of Detroit (Hutchinson was a director); Heritage Foundation; Herbert Hoover Foundation (Hutchinson was a trustee); and St. Paul's Cathedral. (Box 38)
- General Correspondence, arranged alphabetically, Institute For Economic Education to William H. Zinsser (all 1955). Includes large files from M.I.T.; Opinion Research; Spiritual Mobilization; Robert Taft Memorial Foundation; and the Tax Foundation, including financial reports (Box 39)
- Daily appointment books for 1953, 1955, 1956, and 1959; correspondence with Herbert Hoover, June 1953, June 1954, and August 1954; folder marked "1940s"; Hutchinson's testimony in January 1947 before the U.S. Senate Committee on Labor and the Public Welfare; correspondence regarding Hutchinson's split with the National Association of Manufacturers over the NAM's position on labor unions and collective bargaining; and Claude Robinson's 120-page typescript journal of his travels with his family, 19 July - 25 August 1954. (Box 40)
- Detailed listings of speeches, tracts, and other materials:
  - Theodore R. Iserman, "Some Anomalies in the Steel Board's Report and Some Fallacies of `Fact Finding'", 1949; Iserman, "A Comparative Analysis of the Wagner Act, Taft-Hartley Act, the Wood Bill, and the Lesinsky Bill" (1949?); Iserman, "Unsolved Problems of Labor Law," Temple Law Quarterly 21 (April 1948): 334-356; Alfred P. Haale, "Is Private Enterprise Compatible With Christianity"", speech to the Economic Club of Detroit, 27 February 1950; George Romney, "It's Your Ship," speech to the Mortgage Bankers Association, Detroit; John W. Scoville, Labor Monopoly or Freedom? (New York: Committee For Constitutional Government, 1946; Henry J. Weaver, Mainspring: The Story of Human Progress and How Not to Prevent It (Detroit: Talbot Books, 1947); George Romney (Managing Director of the Automotive Council For War Production), Statement to the Senate War Investigating Committee on Manpower Problems and Their Effect on War Production, 9 March 1945; "The Marshall Plan. What It Means to Us," Hutchinson speech to the Economic Club of Detroit, 5 January 1948; and "Memorandum on S. 249," 11 Feb. 1949. (Box 7)
  - Automobile Manufactures Association, 100 Motor Vehicles: A Study of Mass Production and Its Effects on the United States (Detroit, 1948); Raymond Morely's broadcast (29 April 1948) regarding the U.S. and Russia; Rev. Edward A. Keller, "The National Income and Its Distribution," speech at University of Notre Dame, 1947; letter (20 July 1948) from Hutchinson to Morris Sayre, president of the National Association of Manufacturers (NAM) attacking Social Security as a threat to freedom; NAM, "Answer to the CIO's 1948 Wage Case," April 1948; NAM, "International Affairs and Our Internal Economy," 18 September 1948; NAM, "Memorandum on Labor-Management Relations," 21 March 1945; "Public Awareness of NAM Growing Steadily," NAM News 16 (2 October 1948: 4-6; Hutchinson's letter of resignation from the NAM, 13 December 1948; Hutchinson letter to Morris Sayre confirming his resignation, 29 December 1948; "NAM Policy in the Field of Social Security,"; "Memorandum on the NAM Policy in the Field of Social Security," Confidential, 26 October 1948; Victory For Freedom: A Program Adopted by the War and Reconversion Congress of American Industry (New York: NAM, December 1944); NAM, "What Bureaucracy Means to You" (1945); and Dexter Masters and Katherine Way, One World or None, A Report to the Public on the Full Meaning of the Atomic Bomb (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1946). (Box 8)
  - What the Public Opinion Polls Show on the Subject of Labor Legislation, 10 March 1947; Opinion Research Corporation, The Taft-Hartley Law and Its Successor (Princeton, NJ: 1949); Claude Robinson, Taft-Hartley Aims Still Popular With Workers, Look, 26 April 1949; Garet Garrett, The Revolution Was (Caldwell, Idaho: Caxton Printers, 1944); George Romney (vice president of Nash-Kelvinator), It is Already Late: An Appeal For the Removal of Special Excise Taxes on Automotive Products, to the U.S. House Ways and Means Committee, February 1950; Dr. George S. Benson, A Plea For Personal Self-Reliance, in testimony on the Full Employment Bill, 18 October 1945); George McGraw, Jr., one-page advertisement, The Election of November 2, 1948 Gave No Mandate For Socialism,; Spiritual Mobilization, An Appeal to the Religious Forces of America, September 1946, signed by B.E. Hutchinson; Henry C. Simons, Some Reflections on Syndicalism, The Journal of Political Economy 52 (March 1944: 1-25; The Tax Foundation, The Crisis of Centralization,; The Tax Foundation, Tax Outlook (December 1948), special issue on the Hoover Commission; Willima R. Ballard, There is No Mystery About Patents (New York: J. M. Barrett Corporation, 1946); James H.W. McGraw, Jr., one-page advertisement, Now Is the Time To Fight Socialism in Washington, February 1949; and John T. Flynn, The Truth About Pearl Harbor, 1944. (Box 9)
  - Lectures and publications of Leo Wolman regarding labor relations: The American Labor Problem in 1944, speech, Economic Club of Detroit, 6 November 1944; Industry's Policies of Labor Relations, speech, American Iron and Steel Institute, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York, 25 May 1944; Industry-Wide Bargaining (Irvington-on-Hudson, NY: The Foundation For Economic Education, 1948); What Are the Immediate Prospects For Business, Industry and Labor?, speech, Economic Club of Detroit, 19 October 1953; and The Turning Point in American Labor Policy, Political Science Quarterly 55 (June 1940): 161-175. (Box 10)
  - Hutchinson Speeches -- The Church and Industry, at the Second Baptist Church of Detroit, 19 April 1951; The (MIT) Class of `43, Ahoy!, reprinted in The Technology Review 45 (March 1943): 1-4; Statement Made Before the Special Committee on Postwar Economic Policy and Planning, 28 March 1944, U.S. House of Representatives; Statement on Industry-Wide Bargaining and Labor Monopoly made to the U.S. Senate Committee on Labor and the Public Welfare, 4 February 1947; Freedom, Politics, and Businessmen, before the Automotive and Aviation Parts Manufacturers, inc., Detroit, MI, 12 April 1946; Green Light or Red For the Automotive Industry, before the National Association of Taxicab Owners, 22 October 1952 (no place); How Business and Industrial Management and Education Can Cooperate For A Better Metropolitan Detroit, given at a conference between Industry and Education, Hotel Statler, Detroit, 9 May 1944; Inflation and Its Implication, before the National Association of Manufacturers, 3 December 1948 (Box 25)
  - Hutchinson Speeches - - Let Us Get On With the Revolution, before the National Industrial Council, New York City, 4 December 1946; Graduation Day Address, Milton Academy, Milton, Mass., May 1943; Left and Right: Right and Wrong, before the Women's Town Meeting of Detroit, 21 November 1950; Tribute to John L. Lovett at the meeting of the Michigan Manufacturers' Association, 7 April 1953; Remarks at the Men's Corporate Communion Breakfast at St. Paul's Cathedral (Detroit), 22 February 1953: More Talk, before Wittenagemote, 19 February 1937; Our Postwar Outlook, before an Episcopal men's group (no place, no date); Religion, Economics, and Politics, before the Grosse Pointe (Michigan) Memorial Church Men's Association, 5 October 1948; Road Building in the Public Interest, before the Annual Dinner of the Institute of Traffic Engineers, Detroit, MI, 3 October 1947; Social Capitalism: Today's Frontier, before the Columbus Industrial Association, Deshler-Wallick Hotel, Columbus, Ohio, 12 May 1949; and American Business: Capitalist and Competitive!, before the Illinois Manufacturers' Costs Association, at the Palmer House, Chicago, 15 November 1949., Note on reformatted sound recordings: Let Us Get On With the Revolution, an incomplete, dictated version of Hutchinson's speech before the National Industrial Council, New York City, has been digitized. In this speech, he calls himself a revolutionary and calls for a revolution as an extension of the past 2000 years, especially built upon the actions of the Founding Fathers. He opposes both the New Deal and communism. Among his criticism of New Dealers, both Democratic and Republican, is his opposition to price controls, and he singles out rent control. Use copy reference number: 97027_a_0007454 (Box 26)
  - Hutchinson Speeches - - "Social Capitalism: America's Frontier," before the Mississippi Economic Council, Jackson, Miss., 3 November 1949; "Some Facts About the Chrysler Corporation Before and During the War," before the Society of Security Analysts, New York City, 24 October 1945; "Some Postwar Thinking," to the Men's Association of the Grosse Pointe (Michigan) Memorial Church, 8 February 1944; "Some Postwar Thoughts," at the Rotary Club, Detroit, MI, 4 August 1943; "Some Reflections on Practical Idealism," before the "Men of Christ Church," 28 February 1950; "Some Observations on Troublesome Questions," before the Michigan Commercial Secretaries Association, Hotel Statler, Washington, D.C., 29 April 1952; "A United Front For Business," before the Wisconsin State Chamber of Commerce, Pfister Hotel, Milwaukee, 7 November 1947; "What's the Automotive Destination?," before the Sacony-Vacuum Oil Company, Hotel Fort Shelby, Detroit, 9 October 1952; and "Citizen Responsibilities of the Individual," before the Government Research Association, Detroit, 13 December 1945. (Box 27)
  - An Evening With the National Review: Some Memorable Articles From the First Five Years (New York: National Review, 1960), autographed by Bill Buckley, with personal note; Leonard E. Reid, "Conscience of the Majority,"; The Princeton Panel: A New Approach For Gaining Understanding and Support For Competitive Capitalism, prepared by Claude Robinson, with correspondence between Robinson ad Hutchinson, 30 January - 14 March 1956; and Russell Kirk, The American College: A Proposal For Reform (1957). (Box 30)
  - Materials Relating to Chrysler Corporation: B.E. Hutchinson, "Inflation and Its Implications," before the National Association of Manufacturers, Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, New York City, 3 December 1948; "Some Facts About the Chrysler Corporation, November 18, 1954,"; "Chrysler's Answers to Questions Submitted by Standard & Poor Regarding the Future of the Auto Industry," (no date, ca. 1954); The Men Who Made Chrysler Motors (August 1930), "Motor Cars to Munitions," special issue of American Machinist, 11 June 1942; New Worlds in Engineering (1940); "Sit-Down: What's Happened in the Automobile Industry Since Enactment of the National Labor Relations Act... As Told to Congress," testimony before the Senate Committee on Education and Labor by William J. Cronin, Secretary of the Automobile Manufacturers Association, 27 June 1937; Some Facts About the Products and Growth of the Chrysler Corporation (March 1936), also called the "Black Book"; John V. Scoville, Chief Statistician, Chrysler Corporation, "Technology and the Value of Employment," address to the Academy of Political Science, New York City, 25 March 1938; and A Tale of Three Cities (Detroit, MI: Maxwell Motor Company, Inc., 1916), reprinted from The Maxwell Magazine, 1916., 3 copies (Box 31)
  - Materials Relating to Chrysler Corporation: Special issue of Automobile Topics (30 December 1933) devoted to Chrysler's ten-year anniversary; John W. Scoville, Behavior of the Automobile Industry in Depression, address delivered by Scoville, Chief Statistician, Chrysler Corporation, to the Econometric Society, Roosevelt Hotel, New York City, 20 December 1935; Chronology of the Automobile Industry, from the Automobile Manufacturers' Association (1939); The Chrysler Building (New York: Chrysler Tower Corporation, 1930), black velvet cover, Dodge and Diesel (1939?); The Growth of Plymouth (1933); The Growth of Chrysler (Detroit: The Chrysler Corporation, 1928); and Men, Methods, and Machines in Automobile Manufacturing (New York: Automobile Manufacturers Association, 1939)., 32 pages, 3 copies (Box 32)